<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal.atom"/>
  <title>TOPLCUP - JOURNAL</title>
  <updated>2021-04-07T19:39:48+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>TOPLCUP</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/simple-swaps-for-a-more-sustainable-life</id>
    <published>2021-04-07T19:39:48+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T13:01:11+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/simple-swaps-for-a-more-sustainable-life"/>
    <title>SIMPLE SWAPS FOR A MORE SUSTAINABLE LIFE</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<ol>
<li>SWAP DISPOSABLE FOR REUSABLE</li>
</ol>
<p>Let’s start simple: <strong>ditch the single-use coffee cups</strong>. With an estimated 8 million tons of plastic entering our oceans each year, it really is time to invest in a quality reusable cup. Shop the range here.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li>SWAP MEAT FOR PLANT-BASED</li>
</ol>
<p><span>Avoiding meat and dairy is the ‘single biggest way’ to reduce your impact on Earth. And let’s face it, with such good alternatives now readily available, it’s never been easier. Also, get up to scratch on what’s in season, support local farm shops or even grow fruit and vegetables at home.</span><span> </span></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>
<span> </span><span>SWAP THE TUMBLE DRYER FOR THE DRYING RACK </span>
</li>
</ol>
<p> By using less energy, you can help to reduce carbon emissions. There are a number of ways you can save energy at home, including switching off standby appliances, turning your heating down and hanging clothes to dry instead of using a dryer.  </p>
<ol start="4">
<li>SWAP FAST FASHION FOR QUALITY PIECES <span></span>
</li>
</ol>
<p><span>Voting with your feet is one of the most powerful ways to make a difference. With environmental corners constantly cut in the name of money, not only is the process of making fast fashion detrimental, but the majority of clothes ultimately end up in landfill. Do your research, be critical of brands, support sustainable business and don’t be afraid to re-wear, borrow and shop at charity shops. </span><span> </span></p>
<ol start="5">
<li>
<span> </span><span>SWAP HARD COPY FOR SOFT COPY </span>
</li>
</ol>
<p> To avoid wasting paper, choose to receive letters over email and only print off documents if necessary. You could also ask shops to email you your receipt instead of printing it off.  </p>
<ol start="6">
<li><span>SWAP WIPES FOR WASHABLE CLOTHES</span></li>
</ol>
<p>Disposable wipes are <span>made from non-biodegradable plastic fibres and a cocktail of chemicals, Look for reusable alternatives! </span></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/facts-about-fairtrade-for-fairtrade-fortnight</id>
    <published>2021-02-03T16:23:40+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-22T16:44:58+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/facts-about-fairtrade-for-fairtrade-fortnight"/>
    <title>Facts about Fairtrade for Fairtrade Fortnight</title>
    <author>
      <name>susie humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8">
<p>Whether you’re an instant coffee lover, you prefer a slow drip or you’re a fan of the pod machines, check if your favourite brand supports Fairtrade.</p>
<p>#ChooseFairtrade #FairtradeFortnight</p><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/facts-about-fairtrade-for-fairtrade-fortnight">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Fairtrade Fortnight runs from 22<sup>nd</sup> February – 7<sup>th</sup> March and is about encouraging UK companies to share their Fairtrade stories. It’s about raising awareness for people all over the world who cultivate our food and drink, mine our minerals or grow the cotton that makes our clothes. These are the people we rarely think about when we’re putting on our shirt in the morning or drinking our first cup of coffee but in many cases, the people who make it possible for us to wear that shirt of drink that coffee are still being exploited.</p>
<p>Of course, this year is different, not just for those unknown farmers all over the world but for us here in the UK too, we’ve all had a tremendously difficult year. The purpose of this article isn’t to chastise anyone, it’s simply to raise awareness. If just one person reads this and double checks their favourite coffee brand next time they’re shopping, checking for that Fairtrade logo, it’s a successful article.</p>
<p>What is Fairtrade?</p>
<p>In a nutshell, Fairtrade is about making sure farmers in developing countries receive a fair price and work in safe environments to produce the things we see on our shelves here in the UK. It’s about making sure they can focus on sustainability, provide an education for their children and rest safe in the knowledge they’ll be able to put food on their table not just next week, but next year too.</p>
<p>We’ve talked about the importance of Fairtrade in our Journal before, you can read <a href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/understanding-fair-trade-coffee/" title="Understanding Fair Trade Coffee">this article</a>.</p>
<p>What’s Fairtrade Fortnight 2021 about?</p>
<p>Fairtrade Fortnight 2021 is focusing on climate change because it’s countries in Latin America and Africa that are feeling some of the harshest impacts from the climate crisis, but they’ve contributed to it the least.</p>
<p>Brazil is the largest coffee producer in the world, but when it comes to greenhouse gas emissions, they’re higher than the global average. But unlike almost every other country in the world, their high emissions aren’t from burning fuels and natural gasses. Brazil’s greenhouse gas emissions are high because of the trees being cut down and burnt in the Amazon rainforest. </p>
<p>Fairtrade and coffee</p>
<p>According to fairtrade.org.uk, 125 million people are dependant on coffee for their livelihood. when you buy Fairtrade coffee, you’re not just making sure these people have a better quality of life, you’re helping them produce a better-quality coffee bean. Fairtrade also helps these farmers build more sustainable farms, they can invest in cleaner energies and water conservation and because they know they’re getting a guaranteed price for their coffee, they can plan for their future.</p>
<p>They can only do all this with your help. Whether you’re an instant coffee lover, you prefer a slow drip or you’re a fan of the pod machines, check if your favourite brand supports Fairtrade.</p>
<p>#ChooseFairtrade #FairtradeFortnight</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/the-health-benefits-of-coffee</id>
    <published>2021-01-04T13:56:18+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T13:52:29+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/the-health-benefits-of-coffee"/>
    <title>The Health Benefits of Coffee</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>As a general rule of thumb, between 10:00am and midday is the perfect time for a caffeine jolt. This is when your brain might be most grateful for a pick me up and it will see you through to lunch. Here at TOPL HQ, many of us tend to switch to decaf after lunch so we can still enjoy our coffee without losing out on a good night’s sleep.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/the-health-benefits-of-coffee">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>It’s January, a month that’s not especially popular at the best of times, let alone when it follows the Christmas (and 2020) many of us have had but here’s hoping 2021 can only get better. Whilst we’re waiting for life to show signs of returning to normal, we’re also eagerly anticipating the days getting longer and hopefully even some rays of sunshine.</p>
<p>At the same time, January is the month for starting that new health kick. Whether you’re joining the gym, trying out the new running shoes you got for Christmas or just promising yourself you’re never going to overindulge in food or drink ever again, January is the month we all take a good hard look at our health. That’s why we wanted to share with you some lesser-known facts about coffee and the impact it can have on your health.</p>
<p>Did you know…</p>
<p>Caffeine is often associated with causing headaches and if you’re prone to headaches and consume a lot of caffeine, switching to decaf could probably help you. But did you know caffeine can actually help headaches too?</p>
<p>Caffeine is found in lots of over the counter painkillers because they work faster when they can get into your metabolism quicker. It’s also an anti-inflammatory which can help depending on the type of headache so next time you feel a headache coming on, a quick cup of joe could help.</p>
<p>How long does caffeine stay in your system? This is one of those piece of string questions, but caffeine has a half life of around 5 hours. The average cup of coffee contains around 100 milligrams of caffeine, so you’ll still have 50mg in your blood after five hours.</p>
<p>For those of us who don’t speak science, the next obvious question is how much coffee can we drink each day? The NHS says around three to four cups a day is perfectly fine (assuming you’re not prone to certain health conditions or pregnant) and regular coffee drinkers can even experience positive health benefits from their habit.</p>
<p>If you’re worried about your coffee stopping you getting a restful night’s sleep, you probably want to know when you should stop drinking coffee before bed? You shouldn’t consume caffeine up to seven hours before you go to sleep. Even if you find you can drift off without any problems, if you’ve still got caffeine in your system, studies have shown it can contribute to a lower quality of sleep leaving you feeling less well rested when you wake up.</p>
<p>As a general rule of thumb, between 10:00am and midday is the perfect time for a caffeine jolt. This is when your brain might be most grateful for a pick me up and it will see you through to lunch. Here at TOPL HQ, many of us tend to switch to decaf after lunch so we can still enjoy our coffee without losing out on a good night’s sleep.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Sources:</p>
<em>https://www.webmd.com/migraines-headaches/triggers-caffeine </em><br><em>https://www.nhs.uk/news/food-and-diet/drinking-3-4-cups-coffee-day-may-have-some-health-benefits/ </em><br><em>https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/coffee-caffeine-sleep-what-time-stop-drinking-energy-science-a8733661.html</em>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/top-5-gifts-for-coffee-lovers</id>
    <published>2020-11-25T10:38:51+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T14:15:36+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/top-5-gifts-for-coffee-lovers"/>
    <title>Top 5 Gifts for Coffee Lovers</title>
    <author>
      <name>susie humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>It’s been an unusual year, but one reliable constant is the sound of jingle bells which we can all start to hear now. Whether you’re sticking to online shopping for Christmas gifts or getting out onto the high street, here’s some ideas for inspiration for any coffee lovers in your life…</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/top-5-gifts-for-coffee-lovers">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>It’s been an unusual year, but one reliable constant is the sound of jingle bells which we can all start to hear now. Whether you’re sticking to online shopping for Christmas gifts or getting out onto the high street, here’s some ideas for inspiration for any coffee lovers in your life…</p>
<p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">High street coffee shop gift card</span></strong></p>
<p>Most larger chains are offering gift cards on their websites but don’t overlook what’s on your doorstep. If you’re looking for the perfect Christmas gift for a neighbour or someone who lives close by, a gift card from your local coffee shop not only helps support independent businesses in what’s been an incredibly difficult year, but also gives the recipient something to look forward to once we’re allowed out and about again.</p>
<p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Organic coffee gift set</span></strong></p>
<p>Another one that’s easy to find with a quick Google search but again, don’t overlook what’s local to you. Local farm shops and independent delicatessen are a great source for finding coffee gifts sets and hot drink hampers. The added benefit of shopping from your local independent shops is they’re often wonderfully unique so you know the recipient is unlikely to get the same gift from anyone else.</p>
<p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Coffee machine</span></strong></p>
<p>If you want to treat someone special, a coffee machine is the perfect gift. It says you appreciate how hard they often work, and you wish them a little luxury every day. From a budget friendly drip coffee maker that doesn’t take up too much worktop space to a large espresso coffee maker that can be more of an investment appliance, you can scale this gift idea up or down with ease. Just make sure you know how much kitchen space they have before you get too carried away!</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Experience day</strong></span></p>
<p>For the person in your life who has everything, experience gifts are the way forward. Not only is this the perfect gift to avoid environmentally damaging packaging, it suits the person who treasures memories over possessions. From have a go barrister training and learning how to make latte art to tasting sessions for a real coffee connoisseur, an experience day is perfect when you’re looking for something a little bit different.</p>
<p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">TOPLCUP</span></strong></p>
<p>Well, we couldn’t write a whole piece about perfect coffee gifts without pointing out the benefits of a TOPLCUP. Whether you know someone who’s going to be back to commuting soon or they’re going to work from home once the world returns to normal, the TOPLCUP is ideal for anyone always on the go who loves a good cup of coffee. As well as keeping your drink warmer longer than any traditional mug, the Spill Safe technology makes it as perfect for the commute as it does sitting next to any expensive phones and laptops.</p>
<p> </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/understanding-fair-trade-coffee</id>
    <published>2020-11-05T20:16:19+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T14:28:01+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/understanding-fair-trade-coffee"/>
    <title>Understanding Fair Trade coffee</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p> </p>
<p>We’ve talked before about just how much damage single use coffee cups have done (and are still doing) to our planet. But it’s not just the vessel itself that we have a social responsibility to improve – it’s the contents too.</p>
<p>Did you know?</p>
<ul>
<li>The majority of coffee is produced in developing nations, yet the majority of coffee is consumed in first world countries and economies that are industrialised</li>
<li>Coffee is one of the most traded agricultural commodities in the world</li>
<li>Almost one third of the world’s coffee is produced in Brazil</li>
<li>One fifth of the population of Ethiopia is reliant on coffee for their livelihood</li>
<li>The UK is the 8<sup>th</sup> largest importer of coffee</li>
</ul>
<p>Once we start to understand where our coffee actually comes from and where it usually ends up, it’s easy to see why sustainability, fair trade and ethical practices have to be part of every cup we drink. We’ve all heard the term ‘fair trade’, and what’s really encouraging is we’re seeing it more and more on coffee packaging in supermarkets and in high street coffee shops.</p>
<p>What started Fairtrade?</p>
<p>Like any internationally traded commodity, the coffee bean is subject to price volatility. Demand can go up and down, price can be impacted not just by availability but global economics, political changes and weather. Back in the late 1980’s coffee prices plunged and many of the small farmers found they weren’t able to sell their coffee for enough money to cover their running costs.</p>
<p>One of the reasons Fairtrade was set up was to make sure every farmer who wanted it, would be guaranteed a minimum fair price for their coffee. This minimum price would do more than just ensure their running costs were covered; it would ensure they knew exactly how much money they would get allowing them to plan ahead. It would also ensure there’d be enough money to invest in the future and make sure they had the tools and resources for next season too.</p>
<p>What does fair trade coffee actually mean?</p>
<p>According to fairtrade.org.uk, fair trade coffee means making sure the lives of people working on the coffee farms in developing countries have a right to a safe, fair and healthy working conditions. That they get a consistent and fair pay for their work and their produce and everyone is equal.</p>
<p>Around 70% of coffee farmers all around the world are small or independent farms – this means the other 30% comes from large scale coffee farms. Fair trade makes sure the larger farms can’t price the smaller farms out the market when something bad happens.</p>
<p>Every time you’re buying a coffee from a coffee shop or making your own at home and you choose to buy fair trade, you’re helping make sure somewhere out there, a farmer can keep their family housed, fed, educated and safe.</p>
<p> </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/for-the-love-of-coffee</id>
    <published>2020-09-23T16:54:41+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-21T09:40:26+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/for-the-love-of-coffee"/>
    <title>For the Love of Coffee – Has Lockdown Changed Our Drinking Habits?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="UTF-8"><span>Whether you’ve taken the time to make yourself the perfect pour over coffee or you’re getting through the day with your trusty favourite brand of instant, coffee always tastes better hot. </span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/for-the-love-of-coffee">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<div>
<div>
<div>
<ul>
<li>According to reports from Cardiff and Southampton universities, the majority of workers are more productive working from home</li>
<li>Pre-pandemic, around 6% of workers worked from home, by April, 43% had adopted this new way of working</li>
<li>As uncertainty looms as to when we’ll be back in the office, many employers are open to introducing more flexible working</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div></div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Whether you’re back in the office or still working from home, one thing’s for sure; we’ve all had to adapt whilst ensuring our productivity doesn’t drop. Here in the UK, one thing hasn’t changed throughout everything that’s been going on; we all still love a good hot drink. When it comes to tea and coffee, it’s not just the office environment that makes us reach for the kettle, it’s the comforting habit of choice that doesn’t change no matter where you’re working.</p>
<p>It’s not surprising to learn that The Guardian reported sales of tea and coffee increased by £24million in July. If we look at Google’s Trend data, we can see interest for coffee machines increased by 16% from March to April. Here at Topl, we obviously love a good cup of coffee which is why we’ve spent so much time engineering the perfect cup which we’re really excited to share with you. But the reusable coffee cup isn’t just for commuters – don’t get me wrong here, it’s obviously the perfect accessory for anyone on the go – it’s ideal for anyone who’s super busy no matter where they’re working.</p>
<p>Whether you’ve taken the time to make yourself the perfect pour over coffee or you’re getting through the day with your trusty favourite brand of instant, coffee always tastes better hot. By the time you’ve quickly answered that email, joined in that conversation on Slack or participated in a Zoom meeting, your coffee has gone cold in a traditional mug. But if it’s poured straight into your trusty vacuum insulated cup, it’s staying hot for hours. A great design feature of the Topl reusable cup is that its spill safe technology and lockable lid, means it’s not going to get accidently knocked over your laptop. For those working from home at the moment with kids running about, this feature can be a game changer! It means no little hands are reaching for liquid that could potentially scold them and no boisterous play will be sending your cuppa flying.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/reusable-vs-disposable-the-coffee-cup-conundrum</id>
    <published>2020-07-23T10:09:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T14:50:10+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/reusable-vs-disposable-the-coffee-cup-conundrum"/>
    <title>Reusable vs disposable – the coffee cup conundrum</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>Supermarkets no longer hand out free carrier bags and the majority of shoppers usually remember to bring their own bag but we’re still not seeing the same trend when it comes to coffee shops.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/reusable-vs-disposable-the-coffee-cup-conundrum">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<ul>
<li>The UK throws away 2.5 billion disposable coffee cups every year – less than 1% are recycled</li>
<li>There are only three recycling plants in the UK which can deal with drink contaminated recyclables</li>
<li>The UK is one of Europe’s largest takeaway coffee consumers with one in five of us visiting a coffee shop every day</li>
<li>A reusable coffee cup can have a better environmental impact than a paper cup in just one month</li>
</ul>
<p>For years now, we’ve been hearing about the damaging impact of single use plastic. Supermarkets no longer hand out free carrier bags and the majority of shoppers usually remember to bring their own bag but we’re still not seeing the same trend when it comes to coffee shops.</p>
<p>Whilst there’s certainly no denying the rise in use of reusable coffee cups, observe any high street coffee shop and you’ll see more customers walk out with a disposable cup than a reusable one. Most of the larger chains have worked hard to up their recycling game, they offer recycling hubs and discounts to reusable cup customers but why is it so hard? When it comes to disposable hot drink cups, it’s the polyethylene liner that throws a spanner into the recycling works, this liner maybe great at keeping your drink inside the paper cup, but it doesn’t recycle easily.</p>
<p>It’s great that these days, you can drop your single use coffee cup back at the coffee shop and they’ll recycle it. However, for many, the main attraction of the takeaway coffee is you can take it away. By the time you’ve finished it you’re at your office, on the train, back home etc. and that handy recycling point is much further away than a landfill bin.</p>
<p>It’s not just the end of its life that makes the disposable coffee cup so bad for the environment. Before that single use coffee cup even gets used, it’s an ecological problem. Most disposable cups are made from virgin paper pulp rather than recycled paper. This means resource was expended into felling trees, making paper and global shipping only to be used on a single cup of coffee that’s more often than not, relegated to landfill.</p>
<p>Whilst coffee shops do their best to encourage reusable cups and recycling programmes and a ‘latte levy’ is being debated by ministers, it’s the consumer mindset that can have the single biggest impact on this challenge. Just like we’re all so used to taking our bags for life to the supermarket now, we need to adopt the same attitude when it comes to our morning flat white.</p>
<p>Research by RECYC-QUÉBEC looked at the environmental impact of coffee cups and found that the reusable coffee cup would have a better environmental impact than a paper cup in as few as 20 uses. That means a reusable coffee cup used just once a day instead of a paper cup would have a better impact on the environment in just one month if used once a day! With some high street coffee chains offering 50p discounts every time you use your reusable cup; it will have soon paid for itself by this time too!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/scientists-confirm-that-reusables-remain-safe-to-use</id>
    <published>2020-07-14T16:18:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T14:54:55+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/scientists-confirm-that-reusables-remain-safe-to-use"/>
    <title>The &apos;Covid Waste&apos; Crisis</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>The</span><span> global community now faces a new type of pollution.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/scientists-confirm-that-reusables-remain-safe-to-use">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span>Naturally the priority over the past few months has been to mitigate contagion of the virus by wearing face masks and regularly sanitising our hands. </span><br><br><span>However, environmental groups are now coming across alarming quantities of latex gloves, face masks and bottles of hand sanitiser in our oceans. This ‘COVID waste’ indicates a new kind of pollution that escalates the existing plastic crisis.</span><br><br><span>In a signed statement over 200 scientists and pandemic experts now advise that it is imperative that we all begin using reusable face masks and substituting plastic gloves with more frequent hand washing. </span><br><br><span>One thing that we can be certain of is that no matter how long the epidemic lasts, the problems of environmental degradation, climate change and plastic pollution will still be with us when it ends. Plastic and single use products are one of the greatest underlying threats to our future. In recent years, significant progress has been made to change this for the better. We cannot allow the pandemic to derail our progress. Reversion to poor practices will only serve to fuel future global crises. </span><br><br><span>We need to permanently adapt the way we live - for the environment, our health and the lives of future generations.</span></p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0057/3430/1796/files/WhyReuse_medium.png?v=1591271879" alt=""></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/recommitting-to-reuse</id>
    <published>2020-06-04T12:54:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T15:06:28+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/recommitting-to-reuse"/>
    <title>Recommitting to reuse</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>As COVID-19 continues to have an unprecedented impact on our global community, fears about effective ways to return to normality are understandably heightened. Like any complex issue we need to look at real solutions and practices that will help to protect us. Single use items are not one of these solutions.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/recommitting-to-reuse">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>As COVID-19 continues to have an unprecedented impact on our global community, fears about effective ways to return to normality are understandably heightened. Like any complex issue, we need to look at real solutions and practices that will help to protect us. Single use items are not one of these solutions.</p>
<p>To combat the spread of the virus, Starbucks, Costa and several other coffee chains have temporarily banned reusable coffee cups in stores. Current media messaging is that disposable plastic packaging, including disposable coffee cups, are more sanitary then their reusable counterparts as they reduce contact between customer and barista. This seems logical at first glance, but on reflection it becomes obvious that reverting to using disposable cups is not an effective way to combat the continued spread of the virus.</p>
<p>As a customer, you have no way of knowing where a disposable cup has been before your pick it up. Most are made from porous materials that can harbour potentially harmful bacteria, they are stored for long periods of time in public areas, and most importantly, they change hands far more frequently than reusables in the supply chain. Single use items come with disposable convenience, but as we have seen, perceived convenience easily disguises a host of negative issues.<br><br>Plastic and single use products are one of the greatest underlying threats to our future. In recent years, significant progress has been made to change this for the better. We cannot allow times like these to derail our progress. Reversion to poor practices will only serve to fuel future global crises. We need to permanently adapt the way we live - for the environment, our health and the lives of future generations.<br><br>Social distancing is effectively flattening the COVID-19 curve, so there has never been a better time to hone your at-home barista skills. If you do venture to the coffee shop, attention now should be on maintaining the correct hygiene practices. Always wash your hands and retain your lid (there is no reason for your barista or anyone else to touch this). Using your own drinking vessel empowers you to control potentially unhygienic exposure. We encourage you to take time to speak with your local barista about the various actions that can be taken to successfully move through this time of risk and ensure that reuse continues.</p>
<p>One thing that we can be certain of, is that no matter how long the epidemic lasts, the problems of environmental degradation, climate change and plastic pollution will still be with us when it ends.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0057/3430/1796/files/WhyReuse_large.png?v=1591271879" style="float: none;" width="266" height="266"></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/an-epic-espresso</id>
    <published>2020-05-12T17:09:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T15:22:26+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/an-epic-espresso"/>
    <title>Espresso anyone?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>The simple fact of the matter is that your ability to make a truly cafe-grade espresso at home is going to come down to two things</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/an-epic-espresso">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>The simple fact of the matter is that your ability to make a truly cafe-grade espresso at home is going to come down to two things: an investment in quality machinery (we love De Longhi's La Specialista) and your willingness to experiment as a self-taught barista.</p>
<p> Here are a few tips and best practices to get started:</p>
<p><strong>1.    USE THE FRESHEST BEANS</strong><br>Remember, a cup of coffee is only as good as the beans you start with.<br><br><strong>2.    CLEAN YOUR PORTAFILTER</strong><br>Before trying to make your espresso make sure you clean your portafilter. The combination of moisture or leftover grounds will leave your beverage taste over-extracted and bitter.</p>
<p><strong>3.  DOSE CORRECTLY </strong><br>When grinding your gourmet coffee beans, make sure you use the proper amount. This way, you are sure that your extraction is correct, and the proper dosage is dispensed.</p>
<strong>4.    TAMP EVENLY AND CONSISTENTLY</strong>
<p>Tamp the grounds and pack the level. The proper tamp method is to hold your elbow at 90 degrees, rest your portafilter on a level surface and apply equal pressure until the coffee is level.</p>
<strong>5.      TIMING IS KEY</strong>
<p>Insert the portafilter and start brewing immediately after tamping. Place the portafilter back in the machine and get your timer ready. </p>
<strong>6.      BE AWARE OF THE YIELD &amp; BREW TIME</strong> <br>Depending on your machine and the tamp, the deal brewing time is 20-30 seconds. <br> <br> After this, it's all about practice. The key to making a good espresso,<span> </span>is really about tinkering to make sure you have the right grind setting and coffee amount to make sure that the coffee isn't being under or over-extracted. Great espresso can be a tricky art to master, but as lockdown stretches out before us, it’s seems well worth putting in the time to elevate your at-home caffeine game<br> 
<h3>Good luck and let us know how you get on by tagging @toplcup on any social media channel.</h3>
<p> </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/the-perfect-pour-over</id>
    <published>2020-05-11T13:02:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T15:31:40+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/the-perfect-pour-over"/>
    <title>What is pour over coffee?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Pour over coffee tends to have a richer flavour than regular drip coffee as the brewing time is slightly longer. This means the water has more time to extract the flavours from the grounds. Most coffee aficionados will agree this is the superior way to enjoy a cup of coffee.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/the-perfect-pour-over">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h4><span></span></h4>
Pour over coffee tends to have a richer flavour than regular drip coffee as the brewing time is slightly longer. This means the water has more time to extract the flavours from the grounds. Most coffee aficionados will agree this is the superior way to enjoy a cup of coffee.
<h4></h4>
<h4>MAKING POUR-OVER COFFEE ACHIEVES THREE MAJOR THINGS:</h4>
<ul>
<li>One, it'll make you &amp; your friends think you're more of a barista than you actually are</li>
<li>Two, it'll help you feel like you're in an industrial-themed Japanese cafe &amp; not your kitchen</li>
<li>Three, it's just about the cleanest, smoothest cup of coffee you can make.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h3>What’s the best machine to make pour over coffee?</h3>
<p>There are multiple contraptions you can buy to pull this off, but the most widely known are Chemex, which can make pour-over for either 3, 6 or 9 people, and the Hario V60. You can get a starter kit at Allpress. Our beautiful brew stand is from Venture Designs &amp; we have used a Hario Dripper (size 02) &amp; a Coffee Gator Kettle. <br> </p>
<h4>How do I make the perfect pour over coffee?</h4>
<p>Here are our top tips to make the perfect pour over coffee:</p>
<h5>BUY FRESH, WHOLE BEANS</h5>
Remember, a cup of coffee is only as good as the beans you start with. <br> 
<h5>PROPERLY STORE YOUR BEANS</h5>
To keep coffee fresher for longer, make sure you're storing it correctly. While a vacuum sealed container with a one-way valve is advised by experts, a standard air-tight jar will suffice for most. <br> 
<h5>HOW &amp; WHEN YOU GRIND MATTERS</h5>
Grind your coffee immediately before brewing to release the best flavour. Grind size and consistency are important. Pour-over usually requires a medium to medium-fine grind. <br> 
<h5>RATIOS ARE IMPORTANT</h5>
Measure coffee by weight instead of volume. Ideally, the ratio of 1:20 (that's one-part coffee to 20 parts water, or about 7.5g of coffee to 150ml of water). This makes a strong cup of coffee. <br> 
<h5>PRE-INFUSE YOUR GROUNDS</h5>
Pouring hot water over the grounds to help release any remaining carbon dioxide gas left over from the roasting process. Skipping this step will allow the carbon dioxide to repel water during part of the brewing process, effectively making the coffee weaker. <br> 
<h5>BREW AT THE RIGHT TEMPERATURE</h5>
The desired brew temperature for drip coffee is between 90 and 96 degrees Celsius. <br> 
<h5>USE THE FILTERED WATER</h5>
The quality of the water used when brewing is often ignored. You want water that's roughly with a mineral balance of approximately 150 parts per million, achieved by using a Brita filter or equivalent. This ensures the best brew extraction.<span>  </span>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/how-to-make-good-coffee-in-self-isolation</id>
    <published>2020-05-11T12:20:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-07-19T15:43:14+01:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/how-to-make-good-coffee-in-self-isolation"/>
    <title>How To Make Good Coffee In Self-Isolation</title>
    <author>
      <name>Eleanor Humphrey</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<span>For now at least, Covid-19 has claimed our favourite caffeination hotspots - but that doesn’t mean missing out on café quality coffee.</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://toplcup.com/blogs/journal/how-to-make-good-coffee-in-self-isolation">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span>﻿﻿For now at least, Covid-19 has claimed our favourite caffeination hotspots - but that doesn’t mean missing out on café quality coffee. </span></p>
<p>We decided to explore the brew guides of our favourite roasters &amp; get expert advice to elevate our at-home coffee game.Because let’s face it, we can all spare an extra 3 or 4 minutes right now.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for our top tips.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
